There is another way of looking at learning
with the learning control right. So I am going
to think about how can I learn control using
a value iteration kind of an approach right.
So what do I want, so that is my target right
and that is my current estimate of something
right. So remember I am learning the Q function,
so what does the Q function tell me, take
an action whatever is action given in the
Q arguments right.
And then behave optimally that after right,
the first action is whatever I take right
there is no question of optimality or anything
about it.
.
That is being the thing that I am looking
at right, I
should move away very quickly after writing
something on the board that other vegetable
waved me away right. I mean people x kind
of buy that right. So what I am really looking
for when I say Q* I say is expected value
of RT+1 which is what I get for performing
A+ gamma times V* of whatever comes afterwards
correct.
But we know about V* we can write V* in terms
of the Q function how is that V* max it is
a best right there is no p here talking about
optimal value function right. So this is some
term equal to correct. Now we can now do our
stochastic updating rule this is my target
this is my current estimate, so putting this
together I can just write a rule like this
right.
.
So what will be my rule, so target-current
estimate right, let us see people get that
right I mean whatever you are trying to get
earlier we were just trying to take the definition
of the Q function is the expected value of
the return. Now I am looking at the definition
of the Q function as I expected optimal Q
function as expected value of this expression,
but now I am converting that into an update
rule okay.
Now I can put in the rest of it around this
so what is a nice thing here just like in
the expected SARSA I do not have to pick the
action before hand I can pick the action afterwards
also right because I am only doing the max
right. So I do not have to do the pick an
action first and then apply it that I can
move this within the loop try to remove this
I can flip this around basically.
Why is it important why am I so concerned
that is because yeah, so there are a couple
of things here so one thing the most straightforward
answer is it could come back to S in which
case I would have change the value function
right I would have used one year for updating
this here assuming that, that is the A I am
going to take right.
But then I would actually perform a different
A in which case my return see what I was trying
to do here was substitute my return right.
So I am going to see RT+1+gamma this because
that is in there is a sample of the return
right. So if the sample of the return that
means I should actually be sampling according
to whatever updation I am making, but I would
not be doing that I will be sampling my different
action.
If I picked another action after I do the
updation okay so I will be breaking the assumption
that this is a approximation for the return.
So that is the reason we need to pick the
action beforehand and then stick with it right.
And later on when we see how we will be using
a an approximate function value function right,
we talked about contextual bandits right,
we talked about policy parameterization like
that you can use a value function parameterization.
So when you use that you do not have to come
back to the same state right because of the
functional form if I change the value in one
state it may change it in some other state
also. So the whole policy would get up now
messed up so it becomes a little tricky then.
So essentially the trajectory along which
I am doing the updation will be somewhat a
messed-up version of the trajectory which
I am actually taking right.
So it might lead to some trouble in convergence
this way, but that section I will actually
be performing right so it is fine. As long
as that is actually performing it is okay
your question is what you keep changing the
policy anyway right yeah that is why I said
we do not use a explicit representation of
the policy anywhere so it is okay.
So I really do not know what is a policy I
am estimating the value function of is just
that as ? and a go to 0 it will converge to
something at the end right. As long as the
return I am using here when I actually roll
it outright I can roll it out, when I roll
out the return name whatever I am using is
using all the actions I took then I am fine.
What is it, yeah we really on the initial
value of Q that is a policy you start off
this here. So you could actually make it a
valid policy or you could start off with all
zeros in which case it is a uniform random
policy, it will just be call actions with
equal probability to begin with right. So
you can do the same thing here which is empty
space okay.
No not it is equal you just pick it the sequence
happens after you have done the updation okay.
I am picking it according to QST before I
make the update here I am picking it according
to QST after I make the update QST+1 okay
here when I say picker action for QST+1 that
is before this updation is happening.
So if I use Q volt Qnu you will see the theorem
using Q volt here I am using Qnu for picking
the action 80+1, I also put that thing in
bracket I will come to that why I put that
pick action 80 according to QST I put that
in bracket but you can see the difference
between this algorithm and that algorithm
right nothing much except for that simple
change in the update rule if you cool a and
? properly it actually converges to the optimal
policy.
So what will the second algorithm converge
to, optimal policy okay provided cool the
a properly we had decreased a properly will
converge to the optimal policy and this one
if you have to decrease both a and ? properly
it will eventually converge to the optimal
policy. Yeah for a I have the usual stochastic
averaging formula right.
So yeah, tell me 1MIT is one one thing that
you fit the conditions right, so summation
a should be infinity, summation a2 tribulation
infinity right. So that is basically the conditions
for a so as sum over all a is so essentially
I had to put an at there and sum over all
at so just summing over at should be infinity,
summing over at2 should be bounded less than
infinity.
So that is essentially the conditioner because
the at equal infinity tells you that you are
making enough updates and at2 goes to let
mean converges to a point listen infinity
means that you will eventually stop making
updates what, good that is
what the rest of the class is all about, but
so this algorithm 1 the right is probably
the most popular reinforcement algorithm people
use I said when I wrote down SARSA I said
this is the second most popular right.
And that is the first most popular and it
is called Q-learning. So chronologically td0
came first I think which proposed it in like
84 yeah I think which proposed td0 and 84
and short convergence in 88 or something and
Q-learning was proposed by Chris Watkins in
89 and SARSA was proposed by Rummery and Niranjan
may be 91, 92 and I do not know the exact
date sometime around that.
So surprisingly both Watkins and Rummery Niranjan
are from England. So lot of the early algorithms
for RL came from England. And Q-learning is
amazing so what is even more amazing about
Q-learning is that since I do not care what
is the sequence on which you are picking the
actions right here I amusing an approximation
to the optimal return right I am not looking
at the current written.
If I am looking an approximation to the optimal
written so I do not care about the trajectory
in fact in Q-learning I do not even have to
sample according to any trajectory in fact
the next action I execute need not even come
from ST+1, I can arbitrarily reset if I have
a simulation model right I can arbitrarily
reset to some other state right.
And then sample one action from there update
Q-learning and then go and take action from
somewhere else, some other state update you
think you can just do a proper asynchronous
generalized policy iteration kind of an approach,
I just sample from all over the place just
take one step each and keep updating it.
But still it is better to update it along
trajectories like we saw in the argument for
RTDP right, if you updated along trajectories
it is more meaningful because the values should
have more likely to have changed along those
trajectories right. So that is essentially
why we sample according to the trajectories.
So this thing need not be an ? greedy sample
at all right. So I can sample actions arbitrarily
I can just take pick an action AT and ST randomly
okay, I does not have to follow any rule.
So what does this do it just tells me which
action I am going to update next right. If
I am not sampling according to trajectories
it only tell me which action I am going to
update next.
So why do you want to pick according to this,
so that you can just like an RTDP so you can
focus the updates along the most most likely
paths, so what the reason you do it ? greedy
fashion is that you quickly want to converge
to the most likely path that you are going
to take under optimal policy and you want
to do the updates along that most likely path
okay. And that is why you use the ? greedy
sampling for Q-learning.
And so what are the advantage of SARSA, SARSA
you can continue to explore right and while
exploring you learn something that is taking
into account the exploration. So what does
Q-learning do that is why I am saying you
can arbitrarily with Q-learning but if you
choose to behave according to the Q function
you are learning, here it does not take into
account the fact that you are doing exploration
okay. So why would that matter.
.
So it is a simple grid world problem called
the cliff world. So those squares marked in
red of represent a cliff so if the agent wanders
over the cliff is going to get a reward of
-100 and to top it off agent will also die
okay. Basically episode will end the agent
will get a reward of -100 and it goes back
to the beginning and you start all over again
maybe incarnate and you start going all over
again.
And otherwise you get a reward of -1 for every
time step that you move okay. So everything
is deterministic so for every time step that
you move you will get a reward of -1 okay
and yet we will try to get from this start
to the go as quickly as possible no gamma
here gamma is one right whenever I say no
gamma does not mean gamma 0 means gamma is
one okay.
And so what do you think will happen and while
learning I use a ? greedy action selection
? let us say I fix it at 0.1 I am not going
to reduce ? I will fix ? at 0.1 okay. So what
do you think is the policy what do you think
Q-learning will do what do you think SARSA
will do. Well we said both the learn optimal
policies and what is optimal policy here.
Alright so, here you go up there you go left
right, right right, right, so this is the
optimal policy of course if I want to write
down the optimal policy elsewhere maybe I
can just write down arrows everywhere does
not matter right. So I can do down arrows
everywhere or right everywhere except the
last column where I go down this is optimal
policy and there is no question about there
is this is the optimal policy right.
At least for these states right for these
states you have a choice you can either go
right or down for these states this is the
optimal policy right. Okay will Q-learning
find this optimal policy yes, will SARSA find
this optimal policy. In this case it would
not because I have fixed ? at 0.1 right. So
what will SARSA learn, will the show up if
any ? is at a 0.1 let us say. Yeah it may
take a safer and safer row.
If I give you more rows right it will probably
go but then this is too small right it basically
needs to exploratory moves to fall off the
cliff and I given it like 10 moves in which
to take this two exploratory moves. So it
is very high probability it will take those
two exploratory moves right. So it will try
to stay as far away if it just goes here right
this will be just two moves right now this
is three moves.
So that is the reason it will try to go as
far away as possible because the reward is
sufficiently negative I said -100 right so
that is really really bad negative reward.
So it will try to go further and further away
so this is the difference between SARSA and
Q-learning right. So SARSA takes into account
the fact that you are doing the exploration
right, while Q-learning might learn the optimal
policy right, it would also end up killing
you more often while learning the optimal
policy right.
There are also more you are name answers for
this because if you continue to explore right
not this is not exactly name but slightly
less compelling reasons. If you are going
to continue to explore after you finish learning
right it is better to learn the policy through
SARSA then through Q-learning, because Q-learning
assumes that eventually you are going to be
executing the optimal policy right.
But that is a reason for us not to execute
the optimal policy greedily ever why, more
but better than forecast is everyone there
is a reason for us not to use the optimal
policy greedily even after sufficient learning
non-stationary. It is not the stochastic I
am worried about it is a non stationary I
am worried about right.
So if you are convinced that the world is
not changing then great you can start behaving
greedily after some time, but there is a chance
if the world might actually some things might
happen right, or suppose you are robot learning
in a world right. So it is possible that obstacles
can be moved around right. So it do not want
to become so rigid that you are completely
unadoptable when things change right.
So that that is they way, so you want to keep
the option of being able to explore and discover
new things. So you do not want to turn off
your ? ever, but in such cases it is better
to use SARSA than Q-learning, because Q-learning
kind of ignores exploration at all right and
it converges to an optimal policy and then
it sticks there right.
So right and so the problem with the converging
to optimal policy in sticking there is this
right, if I want to keep my ? on and I will
keep falling off the cliff by every one single
move I make wrong where exploratory move I
make I will keep falling off the cliff. So
on the expected reward I get for executing
this optimal policy will be far lesser then
what my agent believes it should be getting
because agent is ignoring the exploration
okay.
So that is the crucial difference between
Q-learning and SARSA that is why you would
like to use SARSA in many cases. Q-learning
is actually good in yeah in some aspects yeah,
there is no danger and the state space is
very large. So why should the size of the
state space matter see it is exploring why
I mean Q-learning can explore much more than
SARSA it right because it ignores exploratory
policy completely you can actually have a
region became completely randomly and still
learn the optimal policy in Q-learning.
In fact that makes Q-learning
of policy method right you can do arbitrary
exploration and still learn the optimal policy
right. So I am at the estimation policy for
me is the optimal policy and the behavior
policy can be something completely random.
So that is one reason you would want to use
Q-learning in a large state space because
I can behave arbitrarily.
So that I get to explore a larger fraction
of the state space, everything will be slow
both will be slow. Why would you think Q-learning
will be slower compared to SARSA. So I am
not a 100% sure about the convergence rates
between ? I mean Q-learning and SARSA
I am not sure about the convergence rates,
I do believe that Q-learning converges faster
than SARSA in general.
And I am not sure about large state space
issues but I will have to look it up. Yeah
but you should know that these are the basic
algorithms right if you want to operate in
large state spaces you will be using something
else over on top of this, this would not be
using plain vanilla Q-learning and SARSA in
large state spaces.
So there are other issues that will come into
play but I am not 100% sure about the comparison
of rates of convergence between Q-learning
and SARSA right great. So any other questions
on these two okay, so I have this three actually
we talked about expected SARSA as well right
and in fact we can think of all kinds of hybrid
algorithms right.
So for example, you can think of an algorithm
that will take one step two steps according
to the current policy and then you say max
right. So what do I mean by that it is something
like this right. So this is, this part is
on policy right, so that class is off policy
right. So that is why it is a hybrid kind
of thing so you can do all kinds of, different
kinds of samplers for your value function
okay.
So in fact it is more common to use the Q
function there, so that is still on policy
everything is on policy but I am using more
of the actual samples and less of the bootstrapping
right. Why I say less of the bootstrapping
because it is discounted by a larger power
of gamma. So the total contribution of the
bootstrap thing will be coming down okay.
So I can do all kinds of modifications to
the return, so in fact there was a time when
we are trying to get a reinforcement learning
agent to play what is the thing called a hockey
right. So somebody in CF, I wanted to do a
project I wanted to get an RL agent to play
air hockey in fact, it was building a physical
system that was going to move the slider around
and he wanted to use RL to control it.
And then he turned out in the simulator at
least that he had built using a three-step
return like RT+1, RT+2, RT+3 then the Q function
of the rest they turned out to give a better
performance or whatever reason right. So it
is kind of a tied to the the stochasticity
in the system and how far ahead is the system
predictable and so on so forth.
So I think it turned out that case for at
least for three steps into the future the
system was more or less predictable and therefore
he could use this kind of writer. So it is
very complicated things right it is not easy
to figure out what is the right look ahead
that they should be using for these returns
okay. So they more or less done with chapter
six.